<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Proclamation anent the poor, and providing correction-houses for them.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Privy Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05526</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1679</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183396</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53299272</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53299272</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180005</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05526)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180005)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2810:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Proclamation anent the poor, and providing correction-houses for them.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Privy Council.</author>
                  <author>Scotland. Sovereign (1694-1702 : William II)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the heirs and successors of Andrew Anderson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini 1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Title vignette: royal seal with initials W R.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Public welfare --  Law and legislation --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Poor laws --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Almshouses --  Law and legislation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  Scotland --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:180005:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:180005:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <p>W R</p>
                  <p>DIEV ET MON DROIT</p>
                  <p>HONI SOIT QUI MAL Y PENSE</p>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>PROCLAMATION</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Anent the Poor, and providing Correction-Houſes for them.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <hi>WILLIAM</hi> By the Grace of GOD, King of <hi>Great-Britain, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith,</signed>
               <salute>To  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈1 span left blank〉</desc>
                  </gap>  Macers of Our Privy Council, Meſſengers at Arms, Our Sheriffs in that part, conjunctly and ſeverally, ſpecially conſtitute Greeting:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>Foraſmuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi> the Extraordinary Dearth and Scarcity for theſe ſeveral years bypaſt, hath hindred the due Execution of the ſeveral Acts of Parliament, and former Proclamations of Our Privy Council, made and publiſhed, anent the providing of the Poor; And that now the ſeaſonable and plentifull Harveſt may Allow and doth Require ſettled and ordered Proviſions to be made for the Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the ſaid Poor, before the approaching Winter: <hi>Therefore,</hi> We with Advice of the Lords of Our Privy Council, Require and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Sheriffs of Shires, and Stewarts of Stewartries and the Heretors, and Commiſſioners of Supply within their reſpective Juriſdictions, To Meet and Conveen upon the ſecond Thurſday of <hi>October</hi> next to come: And there take under Conſideration the Acts of Parliament and former Proclamations of Our Privy Council made anent provideing the Poor: And in proſecution thereof, to lay down ſuch Rules and Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for Maintaining and Subſiſting the poor within the ſeveral Paroches of the ſaid reſpective Juriſdictions as have Reſided within the ſame for theſe three years by paſt, and for ſending away ſuch of the ſaid poor as are wandering Beggars, to the places where they have had their reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pective Reſidences for the laſt three years by paſt, and that in the moſt orderly and Regular Method they ſhall think fit. And for the better, providing and Subſiſting of the ſaid Poor within the reſpective Shires and Stewartries We with Advice foreſaid, Require and Command the Magiſtrats of the ſeveral Burghs after-mentioned, betwixt and the firſt day of <hi>December</hi> next to come, to provide Correction Houſes for Receiving and Intertaining of Beggars, Vagabounds and Idle Perſons within their reſpective Shires, conform to the Acts of Parliament made thereanent, <hi>Viz.</hi> The Magiſtrats of the Burgh of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> a Correction-houſe for the Burgh and Shire thereof. The Magiſtrats of the Burgh of <hi>Dumfreis,</hi> a Correction houſe for the ſaid Burgh and Shire. The Magiſtrats of the Burgh of <hi>Air,</hi> a Correction-houſe for the ſaid Burgh and Shire. The Magiſtrats of the Burgh of <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> a Correction-houſe for the ſaid Burgh and Sheriffdom of <hi>Lanerk.</hi> The Magiſtrats of the Burgh of <hi>Stirling,</hi> a Correction-houſe for the ſaid Burgh and Shire thereof, and Sheriffdom of <hi>Clackmannan.</hi> The Magiſtrats of the Burgh of <hi>Perth,</hi> a Correction-houſe for the ſaid Burgh and Shire thereof. The Magiſtrats of the Burgh of <hi>Dundae,</hi> a Correction-houſe for the ſaid Burgh and Sheriffdom of <hi>Forfar.</hi> The Magiſtrats of the Burgh of <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> a Correction-houſe for the ſaid Burgh and Shire thereof. The Magiſtrats of the Burgh of <hi>Inverneſs,</hi> a Correction-houſe for the ſaid Burgh and Sheriffdom thereof: Each of which Houſes ſhall have a large Cloſs ſufficiently incloſed, for keeping the ſaid Poor people, that they be not neceſſitat to be alwiſe within Doors, to the Hurt and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of their health: And We with Advice foreſaid Require and Command the ſaids Correction-houſes to be provided and in readineſs by the ſaid reſpective Magiſtrats, betwixt and the firſt day of <hi>December</hi> next to come, under the penalty of five hundred Merks <hi>Scots</hi> Money, to be imployed for the uſe of the Poor of the ſaid Shire. And Ordains the Magiſtrats of the reſpective Burghs above-mentioned, to receive the Poor of the the Shires above ſet down, which ſhall be ſent to them at and after the ſaid day, and Intertain the ſame, whether the ſaids Correction-houſes be provided or not. And to the effect the Sheriffs, Heretors Stewarts and Commiſſioners of the ſeveral Shires within this Kingdom may have the ſaid Matter more fully before them, We hereby Ordain and Appoint the Proclamations of Our Privy Council, dated the Eleventh day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred and ninety two years, and the twenty ninth day of <hi>August</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred ninety three years, and laſt day of <hi>July</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred ninety four years, Ratified and Approven by the twenty ninth Act of the ſixth Seſſion of Our current Parliament, to be Reprinted and ſent to the Sheriffs of the ſeveral Shires and Stewartries or their Clerks, to be laid before the ſaid Meeting at the day above-mentioned; And which we with Advice foreſaid, Ordain to be put to punctual and Vigorous Execution in all points: And we hereby Require and Command the Sheriffs of the ſeveral Shires, and Stewartries of Stewartries and Magiſtrats of Burghs to Report a particular Account of their Diligence in the Premiſſes to the Lords of Our privy Council betwixt and the firſt day of <hi>February</hi> next to come, as they will be anſwerable at their higheſt perril. OUR WILL IS HEREFORE and we Charge you ſtrictly and Command, that incontinent theſe Our Letters ſeen, ye paſs to the Mercat Croſs of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and Rema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Mercat-Croſſes of the hail Head-Burghs of the ſeveral Shires and Stewartries within this Kingdom, and there in Our Name and Authority by open Proclamation make Intimation hereof: And Ordains Our Solicitor to tranſmit Copies hereof, and of the ſeveral Proclamations above-writen to the Sheriffs and Stewarts of the ſeveral Shires and Stewartries and their Clerks, to the effect Copies of this Proclamation may be ſent to the Miniſters in the ſeveral Paroch-Churches, to be by them Read upon the firſt Lords day immediatly proceeding the ſaid Meeting of the Sheriffs, Stewarts and Heretors upon the ſaid day of their Meeting. And Ordains theſe preſents to be Printed</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given under Our Signet at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> 
                  <date>the Fifteen day of September, and of Our Reign the Eleventh Year, 1699.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Per Actum Dominorum Secreti Concilii.
<hi>GILB. ELLIOT</hi> Cls. Sti. Concilii.</signed>
               <lb/>
GOD Save the King</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Printed by the Heirs and Succeſſors of <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> Printer to the King's moſt Excellent Majeſty, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
